Guide to the Gennadii Panin Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Gennadiĭ Panin papers
1897-1985
GEN MSS 294
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
8.75
(10 boxes)
A collection of bound volumes and other papers. There are 47 bound volumes, typewritten and with tipped-in clippings, about general poetics and acrostics, and containing copies of Panin's writings (poetry, prose, memoirs, diaries), and correspondence. The volumes include a 26 volume work on the history of the acrostic. The papers also include correspondence, photographs, loose clippings, and printed matter on related subjects.
Panin, Gennadiĭ Gennadievich
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Gennadii Gennadievich Panin and transferred to the library in 1989.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
GENNADII GENNADIEVICH PANIN (1895-1990)
Gennadii Gennadievich Panin was born September 25, 1895 in Moscow, the son of an engineer. His early childhood was spent in the northern town of Viatka, and from 1903 in Petersburg. In 1906, his mother Varvara Fedorovna abandoned the family, and Panin spent the following years moving between her new household and that of his father Gennadii Andreevich. He lived with an aunt in Kazan' for several years before moving to the Crimea in 1912 to rejoin his father. Panin graduated from school in Simferopol' in 1914 and returned to Petersburg to attend a technical college. He was drafted in 1916 but did not see action; in 1917 he returned to Simferopol' where he began to take active part in local literary circles and publish his own poems. Panin fought with the anti-Bolshevik Volunteer Army in the Crimea and remained there after its defeat, although his father evacuated and eventually made his way to the United States. Panin subsequently served in the Red Army, worked for the newspaper Krasnyi Krym, and pursued a number of careers before becoming an accountant in 1927. In 1925 he married Frantsiska Matveevna Shneider, with whom he remained until her death in 1984.
A new chapter in Panin's life began with his detainment by the NKVD (the People's Commissariat for Internal Affairs, precursor of the KGB) from June to December 1938. At the start of the war, due to his wife's German ancestry, the Panin family was exiled to the Caucasus. When the Germans occupied the territory, Panin returned to Simferopol' and worked for the newspaper Golos Kryma. In 1943 Panin's translations of the Armenian poet Simeon Babiian were published in two small collections. In late 1943, Panin left the Crimea together with the evacuating Germans. After spending several years in camps for displaced persons in Germany, Panin followed his daughter Liudmila to America in 1950 and settled in Shelton, Connecticut, not far from where his father had settled. Tragically, one of Panin's first publications, of which multiple copies are preserved among his papers, was his father's obituary.
Panin's life in the United States was a combination of hard work at a local factory and a satisfying existence on the periphery of émigré literary circles. He corresponded with many greater and lesser writers and poets, generously bestowing them with acrostics of his own composition. In time, Panin's acrostics became a staple of such newspapers as Novoe russkoe slovo and journals like Sovremennik and Novyi zhurnal; in the latter he also published an article on acrostic theory. His love for acrostic poems found its greatest expression in a twenty-six-volume collection of the poems in various national literatures Materialy k istorii akrostikha, mezostikha, telestikha. So vremen Assirii i Vavilona do nashikh dnei. Panin included all of the poems he could find in all of the many languages in which he claimed competency, from Assyrian to Lithuanian. Panin also collected his own poetry, several short-stories, his memoirs "Putiami poter'", along with his diaries and correspondence into bound volumes. All in all, Panin completed forty-one homemade volumes before his death, and they constitute the bulk of his papers. Panin died on January 13, 1990, and is buried at Evergreen Cemetary in Ansonia, Connecticut.
Scope and Contents
Series I: Bound Volumes consists of Panin's bound compilations of his own papers and poetry and of the works of others. Most of the volumes contain typewritten pages by Panin interwoven with clippings, letters, photographs and documents. The three-volume compendium of correspondence consists mainly of transcriptions of letters to Panin; few original letters are present. Several volumes, including vol. 24 of Materialy... and the first three volumes of his untitled work on poetic theory, include complete copies of books by previous scholars of versification with Panin's annotations, addenda, and clippings. All volumes are meticulously paginated, indexed, and cross-referenced.
Series II: Letters to G. G. Panin includes letters from émigré authors and scholars of Russian literature and history, including I. A. Artamonov, Ella Bobrova, George Cheron, B. A. Filippov and Vladimir Samarin. This series does not represent the entirety of Panin's quite large correspondence, most of which was probably sold to the Thomas P. Whitney Museum and later transferred to the Amherst Center for Russian Culture at Amherst College in Massachusetts. The letters are supplemented by the transcriptions Panin bound into the three volumes Iz pisem adresovannykh mne.
Series III: Photographs includes portraits of family members and literary acquaintances, and Series IV: Other Papers consists mainly of materials apparently left over from the bound volumes: multiple copies of Panin's poetry (dating from 1917 to 1984), publications where Panin is mentioned, page designs, and the works of correspondents. The two letters from K. P. Pobedonostsev are presumably the vestige of Panin's extensive autograph collection, some of which is also kept at the Amherst Center for Russian Culture.
Acrostics; Poetics -- History and criticism; Russian poetry -- 20th Century; Russia -- Emigration and immigration -- 20th Century; Berezov, Rodion, 1896-1988; Buldeev, Aleksandr Ivanovich; Burli͡uk, David, 1882-1967; Filippov, Boris, 1905-1991; Klenovskiĭ, Dmitriĭ I., 1892-1976; Panin, Gennadiĭ Gennadievich; Samarin, Vladimir
- Bound Volumes, Series I
  Scope and Contents
  Akro-mezo-telestikhi
  - 1 (pp. 1-120), 1964 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 2 (pp. 121-284/2), 1964 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 3 (pp. 285-597/a), 1969 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Tom 4 (pp. 598-1005), 1969 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Akrostikh, mezostikh, telestikh: popytka prosledit' put', imi proidennyi, s drevneishikh vremen do nashikh dnei, pp. 1-32, I-VI (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Akrostikhi
    - 1 (pp. I-CCCIII, 1-327), 1974 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Also entitled: "Opyty akrostikhi mezostikhi telestikhi: god 1970 i posle," chast' 5-aia
    - 2 (pp. 328-668, clippings and index) (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - [3] Moe mne: Akrostikhi (669-822); "Opyt khronologii russkogo akrostikha" (1-110), 1983 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Iz pisem mne adresovannykh
    - Chast' pervaia. (pp. 1-493), 1965-69 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Chast' vtoraia. (pp. 494-1101, indices), 1969-72 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Chast' tret'ia. (pp. 1-892), 1972-75 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Materialy k istorii akrostikha, mezostikha, telestikha. So vremen Assirii i Vavilona do nashikh dnei. Sobral i obrabotal Gennadii Panin.
    - 1. Russkii akrostikh. Chast' 1., 1966 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - 2. Russkii akrostikh. Chast' 2, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - 3. Russkii akrostikh. Chast' 3, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - 4. Frantsuzskii akrostikh, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - 5. Nemetskii akrostikh. Tom 1, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - 6. Nemetskii akrostikh. Tom 2, chast' 1., 1966 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - 7. Nemetskii akrostikh. Tom 2, chast' 2., 1966 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - 8. Ital'ianskii akrostikh, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - 9. Angliiskii akrostikh. Chast' 1, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - 10. Angliiskii akrostikh. Chast' 2, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - 11. Angliiskii akrostikh. Chast' 3, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - 12. Angliiskii akrostikh. Chast' 4, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - 13. Grecheskii akrostikh, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - 14. Akrostikhi ukrainskii, slovenskii, pol'skii, bolgarskii i russkii, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - 15. Latinskii akrostikh. Chast' 1, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - 16. Latinskii akrostikh. Chast' 2, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - 17. Latinskii akrostikh. Chast' 3, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - 18. Latinskii akrostikh. Chast' 4, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - 19. Latinskii akrostikh. Chast' 5, 1970 (Box 5, Folder 30)
    - 20. Latinskii akrostikh. Chast' 6, 1970 (Box 5, Folder 31)
    - 21. Akrostikhi Armenii, Vengrii, Gollandii, Vizantii, Ispanii, Litvy, Germanii, Portugalii, Rossii, Siama, Sirii, 1970 (Box 5, Folder 32)
    - 22. Akrostikhi na Ivrit i Idish, 1970 (Box 5, Folder 33)
    - 23. Akrostikh: terminologiia, bibliografiia, koe-chto iz svidetel'stv o nem, 1970 (Box 5, Folder 34)
    - 23a. Akrostikh: terminologiia, bibliografiia, koe-chto iz svidetel'stv o nem. Okonchanie, 1970 (Box 5, Folder 35)
    - 24. Angliiskii akrostikh: akrostikhi L. Skotta, 1970 (Box 5, Folder 36)
    - 25. Akrostikhi, ne voshedshie pochemu- libo v knigi 1 po 24 vkliuchitel'no, 1970 (Box 6, Folder 37)
  - Napechatannoe, 1917-45 (pp. 1-281, index) (Box 6, Folder 38)
  - Terminy nauki o stikhe ustami poetov i prozaikov
    - Chast' 1-ia (pp. 1-528), 1980 (Box 6, Folder 39)
    - Chast' 2-ia (pp. 529-1101), 1980 (Box 6, Folder 40)
    - Chast' 3-ia. (pp. 1102-1552, index), 1980 (Box 6, Folder 41)
  - Untitled work on poetic theory, incorporating Shul'govskii, Uchenie zvukovoi garmonii stikha, clippings, holograph additions and annotations
    - 1 (pp. A-F, I-XL, 1-288), n.d. (Box 6, Folder 42)
    - 2 (pp. 289/0-404/xxxiv), n.d. (Box 6, Folder 43)
    - 3 (pp. 405/000-543, notes), n.d. (Box 6, Folder 44)
    - 4. "Khrestomatiia po stikhologii: opyt posobiia dlia izuchaiushchikh nauku o stikhe. (pp. 543/a-1418), n.d. (Box 7, Folder 45)
  - Untitled: includes "Ispytanie strakhom (povest')" (pp. 1-93), "'Edinstvennaia' v mire, deistvitel'no 'demokraticheskaia' ... glazami inostrantsev" (201), [misc] (202-226), n.d. (Box 7, Folder 46)
  - Untitled: includes Diary, 1943-48 (pp.1-764), stories (765-798), "Putiami poter'" (memoirs) (801-963), [misc] (964-1000, I-LXIV), Diary, 1949 (LXV-LXVII), 1943-49 (Box 7, Folder 47)
  - Untitled: Diary, 1949-56 (pp. 1-296, index) (Box 7, Folder 48)
- Letters to G. G. Panin, 1979-82; Series II
  - Artamonov, Igor Aleksandrovich, 1979-82 (Box 8, Folder 49)
  - Bobrova, Ella, 1979-85 (Box 8, Folder 50-51)
  - Campbell, Robert, 1953-54 (Box 8, Folder 52)
  - Cheron, George, 1983-85 (Box 8, Folder 53-54)
  - Filippov, Boris Andreevich, 1979-85, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 55)
    Pseudonym of B. A. Filistinskii
  - Guidoni-Rumiantseva, Galina, 1979-80 (Box 8, Folder 56)
  - Guerra, René, 1981-83 (Box 8, Folder 57)
  - London, Igor' Danilovich, 1953-65 (Box 8, Folder 58)
  - Pestrovo, Klavdiia Prokof'evna, 1981 (Box 8, Folder 59)
  - Pol'chaninov, R., 1977 (Box 8, Folder 60)
  - Radionov, G. E., 1980 (Box 8, Folder 61)
  - Sokolov, Vladimir Dmitrievich, 1980-85 (Box 8, Folder 62)
    Pseudonym: V. Samarin
  - Sztein, Emmanuil Alekseevich, 1977 (Box 8, Folder 63)
  - Tiurin, A., 1984 (Box 8, Folder 64)
- Photographs, Series III
  - Lists from covers of envelopes containing photographs (Box 8, Folder 65)
  - Panin, Gennadii Gennadievich, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 66-69)
  - THE PANIN FAMILY
    - With daughter Liudvina, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 70)
    - With family, 1968 (Box 8, Folder 71)
    - With wife and Ekaterina Golovko (Box 8, Folder 72)
    - Panina, Frantsiska Matveevna, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 73)
    - The Kishevskii (Kiszewski) family, 1948-56 (Box 8, Folder 74-75)
  - PANIN IN GROUPS
    - With Anastasiia Abrushevskaia, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 76)
    - With Rodion Mikhailovich Berezov
      - Photograph, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 77)
      - Framed photograph with poems by V. Pereleshin on verso, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 78)
    - With Aleksandr Ivanovich Buldeev
      - Photograph, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 79)
      - Framed photograph with note on verso, 1963 Dec 21 (Box 8, Folder 80)
    - With David Burliuk and Aleksis Rannit (Box 8, Folder 81)
    - With D. Kandurov and daughter (Box 8, Folder 82)
    - With colleagues at Krasnyi Krym, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 83)
  - PHOTOGRAPHS OF OTHERS
    - Berezov, Rodion Mikhailovich: framed with autograph on verso, 1970 (Box 9, Folder 84)
    - Berner, Nikolai Fedorovich, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 85)
    - Klenovskii, Dmitrii Iosifovich
      Pseudonym of D. I. Krachkovskii
      - Photograph, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 86)
      - Photograph: framed, with signed holograph poem on verso, 1965 (Box 9, Folder 87)
      - Zavarova, Anna Vladimirovna, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 88)
- Other Papers, Series IV
  - CLIPPINGS BY G. G. PANIN
    - Poems, 1917-71, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 89-94)
    - "Moi stikhi": typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 95)
    - "Pamiati Dm. Klenovskogo": offprint, 1947 (Box 9, Folder 96)
    - "Khronologicheskii perechen' napechatannogo, 1917-52": typescript, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 97)
      Bibliography continued up to 1985
    - Poems, 1921-82, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 98-100)
    - Issue of Pravoslavnaia Rus', 1977 Aug 14 (Box 9, Folder 101)
    - Issue of Rodnye dali, 1979 (Box 9, Folder 102)
    - Issues of Seiatel' istiny, 1974-84 (Box 10, Folder 103-107)
    - Works, incl. "Chuzhaia elka", 1962-77 (Box 10, Folder 108)
    - By and about G. G. Panin, 1953-77 (Box 10, Folder 109-110)
    - Unused designs for bound volumes (Box 10, Folder 111)
    - Bibliographical list, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 112)
  - MISC PAPERS
    - Al'mendingen, V. V.: offprints of articles on the White Movement, 1962-66 (Box 10, Folder 113)
    - Cheron, George: Offprints of articles on Mikhail Kuzmin, possibly removed from correspondence, 1981-84 (Box 10, Folder 114)
    - Pobedonostsev, Konstantin Petrovich: 2 ALS, with holograph annotations of G. G. Panin, 1897 (Box 10, Folder 115)
    - Rannit, Aleksis. "O poezii i poetike Valeriia Pereleshina": offprint, with mention of G. G. Panin, 1976 (Box 10, Folder 116)
    - Rogozhin, N. P. "Literaturno- khudozhestvennye al'manakhi i sborniki, 1918-27: photocopy with holograph annotations of G. G. Panin, with mention of G. G. Panin, 1960 (Box 10, Folder 117)
    - Rubanov, L. S. "Klub 'Mednyi vsadnik'": photocopy, annotated, with mention of G. G. Panin, 1966 (Box 10, Folder 118)
    - Book catalogues, with xerox of poem by G. G. Panin, 1966-70 (Box 10, Folder 119)
    - "Yale University Library: Slavic and East European Collections Accessions List": annotated by Aleksis Rannit, with mention of G. G. Panin, 1969 (Box 10, Folder 120)